Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College M Street Campus Collection, circa 1875-1939 MVC0002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College M Street Campus Collection
circa 1875-1939
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0002
6.25 Linear Feet 8 document boxes, 1 slim document box, 2 flat boxes
M Street was the second location of Mount Vernon Seminary, founded in Washington, D.C. in 1875. The school officially began operating from its M Street location in 1880. Mount Vernon Seminary and College merged with The George Washington University in 1999. This collection contains photographs, artifacts, school event and club records, student scrapbooks and other student materials created during the school's time on M Street. The materials range in date from circa 1877-1939.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: Photographs, Artifacts, Mount Vernon Seminary records, and Alumnae scrapbooks, correspondence, and diplomas.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical / Historical
In the summer of 1880, Mount Vernon Seminary moved from its first location on F Street to 1100 M Street. Elizabeth Somers originally purchased two adjoining mansions and converted them into school buildings. She added to the M Street houses by building new classrooms, a conservatory, music room, and chapel. Within the next few years, Somers purchased three additional houses and oversaw their complete renovation.
While located on M Street, Mount Vernon Seminary grew to more than 150 pupils. The Mount Vernon Alumnae Association formed in 1885 and held its first reunion in 1886 on the M Street campus.
In 1917, Mount Vernon Seminary moved to a new campus on Nebraska Ave.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains photographs, artifacts, school records, student scrapbooks and othe student materials. The materials range in date from circa 1877-1939.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. Collection transferred to Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Dormitory life; Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Students; Hensley, Adelia Gates; Somers, Elizabeth J.; Mount Vernon Seminary
- Photographs, circa 1877-1915; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This photographs in this series include student portraits, student candids, exterior and interior photos of campus, campus events, and off-campus outings. The series includes multiple cyanotypes of dorm rooms and the M Street chapel. The photographs range in date from circa 1877-1915.
  - Student portraits, portraits of Adelia Gates Hensley and Elizabeth Somers, circa 1877-1897; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Small photographs, 1880; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Copy negatives (called inter-negatives), 1880-1910; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Student group portraits and students in costumes, 1885-1917; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Nautilus Club, 1887-1888; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Alpha Tau Pi Rho Society, 1890; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Student portraits, 1890-1910; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Women in costumes titled "Dramatics in the Nineties", circa 1890-1899; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook pages containing candids of studentss and exteriors of M Street, 1892-1910; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Interior shots of music room, dining room, exterior, library, and drawing room, cyanotypes, 1893-1901; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sightseeing in DC, 1897; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Student portraits (1 of 2), 1898-1920; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Student portraits (2 of 2), 1898-1920; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Luette Ruth Spitzer photo album part 1, 1899-1901; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Luette Ruth Spitzer photo album part 2, 1899-1901; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Luette Ruth Spitzer photo album part 3, 1899-1901; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Grace B Law and Jeroma Cartwright photo album, 1901-1903; Series 1 (Box 1)
  - Barge party and Easter photographs, circa 1903; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Student candids, 1904; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Exterior photographs, 1904-1909; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dorm life and students by the tennis courts, 1910; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Women's suffrage movement parade, 1913; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Students candids, 1914; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Students in a theater production, 1914; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Junior banquets, 1914-1918; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - White House lawn event with Seminary students, 1915; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Portrait of Katherine E. Hill, faculty, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Science class, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Artifacts, circa 1880-1917; Series 2
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains artifacts belonging to students of Mount Vernon Seminary as well as artifacts from the school itself including signs displaying school rules and a personal mirror/frame. The objects in this series range in date from circa 1880-1917.
  - Class of 1914 small metal sign, Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Mirror/frame (silver plate), circa 1910; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Mirror from the elevator rescued by Clara Hawkins Willett, undated; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Print block of Mrs. Somers, Mrs. Hensley, and Mrs Cole; stamp with shield, circa 1915; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Signs "Do Not Run..." and "No Admittance", circa 1880-1917; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Mount Vernon Seminary records, circa 1880-1939; Series 3
  This series contains records from Mount Vernon Seminary, including campus event pamphlets, honor rolls, club meeting minutes, and two scrapbooks containing programs from special events and services. The materials in this series date from circa 1880-1939.
  In order to keep all book plates together, one book plate from 1939 is included in this series.
  - Book plates, 1910-1939; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and report cards, 1882-1905; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Drawing of M Street campus, undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Event pamphlets (plays, graduation), 1880-1917; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Honor Rolls 1907-1908, 1913-1914, 1907-1914; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Honor Rolls 1914-1915 and 1919-1920, 1914-1920; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Laying of the cornerstone for the Nebraska Ave. campus records, 1916; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - MVS factbook class of 1902, Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - MVS 1876-1909 scrapbook part 1, Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - MVS 1876-1909 scrapbook part 2, Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - MVS 1876-1909 scrapbook part 3, Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - MVS 1876-1909 scrapbook part 4, Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - MVS 1876-1909 scrapbook part 5, Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - MVS 1876-1909 scrapbook part 6, Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - MVS 1876-1909 scrapbook part 7, Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - MVS 1876-1909 scrapbook part 8, Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - MVS 1910-1924 scrapbook part 1, Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - MVS 1910-1924 scrapbook part 2, Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - MVS 1910-1924 scrapbook part 3, Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - MVS 1910-1924 scrapbook part 4, Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - MVS 1910-1924 scrapbook part 5, Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - MVS 1910-1924 scrapbook part 6, Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - MVS 1910-1924 scrapbook part 7, Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - MVS 1910-1924 scrapbook loose programs, Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Nautilus book, 1887; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Optima Club, circa 1910; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - The Order of the Lily, 1911; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - The Order of the Lily, Bertha Vernell Bush, Series 3 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - "Our Alma Mater Glorious" score, 1910; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Shakespeare club notebook, 1901; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Alumnae scrapbooks, correspondence, and diplomas, circa 1875-1914; Series 4
  This series contains student-made scrapbooks, letters to and from Minnie Swormstedt (MVS class of 1882), a student's autograph book and diplomas of two Seminary students. The scrapbooks contain photographs of campus life at Mount Vernon Seminary, correspondence, programs from campus events, and other ephemera (including materials like magazine advertisements, newspaper headlines, chewing gum wrappers, and off campus event programs.) Many of the scrapbook pages contain written anecdotes from the owner. The autograph contains messages from friends and acquaintances. Some are written in elaborate calligraphy and intricately decorated. The materials in this series date from circa 1880-1914.
  - Alma Schmidt scrapbook front and back covers, 1914; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Alma Schmidt scrapbook part 1, 1914; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Alma Schmidt scrapbook part 2, 1914; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Alma Schmidt scrapbook part 3, 1914; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Diplomas, India Bell Veder Fleming (1906) and Jeroma Brooks Cartwright (1903), 1903-1906; Series 4 (Box 11)
  - Jean Fitch scrapbook part 1, 1903-1904; Series 4 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Jean Fitch scrapbook part 2, 1903-1904; Series 4 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Jean Fitch scrapbook part 3, 1903-1904; Series 4 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Jean Fitch scrapbook part 4, 1903-1904; Series 4 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Jean Fitch scrapbook part 5, 1903-1904; Series 4 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Jean Fitch scrapbook part 6, 1903-1904; Series 4 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Mary Stuart autograph book, circa 1875-1878; Series 4 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Eleanor A. Golden 6920 Blue Miss Fort Wayne, IN
  - Minnie Swormstedt's letters, 1880-1882; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Minnie Swormstedt's letters, photos, and bill of tuition, 1881-1882; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Minnie Swormstedt's photocopied letters from her family #1, 1881; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Minnie Swormstedt's photocopied letters from her family #2, 1881; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Minnie Swormstedt's letters, 1881-1882; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 5)